Associated with for five
generations.
What your dog called? Nellie.
She's beautiful. Has she always
been on board?
Pretty much, yes, she comes to work.
Customers love,
especially the children.
Dani, how long have you and your family
been involved in the ferry crossing?
The first member of my family
was involved was in the late 1800s.
He is my great, great uncle,
Benjamin Cross.
Then, basically, a member of my family
has been doing it ever since then.
I gather the ferry's been running
a lot longer than that?
Yes, the first recorded crossing was
1236 - that's nearly 800 years ago.
At that time it was a rowing boat
and they used to charge ha'penny
per person and per horse.
Goodness how they rowed
a horse across, I don't know.
Has it always been a rowing boat?
Initially, it was a rowing boat.
They did try to build
a bridge in the 1800s.
The Harbour Commissioners wanted to
do that but it was too expensive.
They decided to put in a pontoon
chain ferry,
which would take two cars at a time.
Sure.
A lot of locals were living here
and that was the only way across
because there was no bridge
further up. Yeah.
The pontoon ferry from the 1880s
was in turn replaced by a new
and improved steam ferry
in the 1920s called The Blyth.
How long did the chain ferry last?
What happened in the Second world
war, the army used to come across
but they didn't pay.
The service went into disrepair
because there was no money. Yeah.
They moored it up and then,
eventually,
the pontoon just sort of ended up
sitting on the mud
and that was the end of that.
After hundreds of years
of crossings, both communities
were cut off from each other but
Dani's family came to the rescue.
In 1940, her great,
great-uncle, Old Bob Cross,
enlisted his brother, Ernie.
Together, using a fishing boat,
they resurrected the old rowing boat
service, which still operates today.
So who took over from Bob and Ernie?
That was Young Bob, Old Bob's son.
He did the ferry in the 1970s
and 19805.
He became a bit of a celebrity because, at that time,
the ferry turned from a necessity to a novelty
and even made the front page of the
New York Times at one point. Really?
He became quite a celebrity.
Local hero? Something like that.
When did your father get involved?
From about the age of 12,
he started helping his great grandad,
who was Old Bob, on the ferry
and he taught him the tricks
of the trade and Bob and Dad
they were quite famous for their
smoked fish - kippers and herrings,
because they had a smokehouse.
It was one of the things do
around here, really? Yeah.
When did your father start to
teach you to row?
I can't really remember, it must've
been from six or seven.
I used to sit on the boat with him and watch
him talk to the customers, stroke the dogs
and gradually he would let me
take one oar and then I would
sit on his lap and do them together
and he would teach me the tides.
I've basically grown-up knowing
all about the ferry and how it works.
It literally is handed
down from father to daughter? Yeah.
And you obviously clearly get
job satisfaction,
I can see you're really
passionate about it.
I think it's working outdoors, for
me, is wonderful and the exercise.
Also, meeting the people.
There are so many people
who come over.
From year to year you gain
your friends and the customers,
you see them every year and you get to
know what's going on in their lives.
It's the continuity
that I really enjoy.
Dani's keen to keep
the tradition alive
and not one to keep her passengers
waiting.
Jump on. Morning, everyone.
Some regulars have turned up to get
across, including Rita and her grandson.
So, Rita, how long
have you been using the ferry?
I've been using
the ferry for 61 years now.
Gosh, you don't look old enough!
You must have been born in the boat!
I was born in walberswick.
I was born in the village. Right.
My mother still lives here.
What about you? I built the ferry.
You built this ferry?
You're a shipwright, aren't you?
That's correct. A lovely trade.
Yeah. Gosh!
What do you think of Dani
continuing the family tradition?
Southwold without the ferry
wouldn't be Southwold, would it?
It's got to have a ferry.
The first one I built
was 61 years ago.
I have never rowed the boat.
Are you...? No.
It's never too late, is it?
THEY LAUGH
It's not too late for Dani's son,
Charlie, or nephew, Oscar.
Are you going to take over
the business one day? No, Oscar is.
Is he? Yeah.
I want to do something different.
You want to do something different!
ALL LAUGH
well, I can't think of a better
way to travel
and make friends at the same time.
Nellie, are you going to jump over?
Long may the tradition
of the Southwold
to walberswick ferry continue.
Yes, there's a lot of people,
isn't there?
Welcome back to lckworth House.
And, at the valuation table,
Adam's about to get a bit
of religious education.
Damaris. Your name is Damaris?
It is. Damaris, that's a very
unusual name.
It comes from the book of Acts
in the Bible. It's a biblical name.
Damaris was a follower of Saint Paul.
Have you met any others?
I met one once, I taught one once.
Where did you get this copper from?
When I was first married
which was in 1964,
we wanted a coal bucket
and we went to the local market.
Where was that, then? In Clitheroe.
Clitheroe!
Are you a Lancashire lady?
Yes, I'm from that area. Very good.
We saw this but, of course,
it was all black and horrible
and I didn't realise
what it would look like.
Yes, it's come up beautifully,
hasn't it?
I've cleaned it ever since. Have you?
I've always cleaned it, yes.
Do remember what it cost you? I do.
That's a Lancashire lady for you.
Dare I tell you? All right.
Ten shillings.
That's not that much, is it'!
No, Sop. Sop'.!
It was a lot then, though.
Of course it was.
I wanted to know really
how old it was.
Well, that's an easy one, really,
because of the style
of decoration to it.
It's very much the Art Nouveau,
Arts and Crafts style.
I thought it was Arts and Crafts.
Yeah, it's sort of 1900s... Yes.
...where this was very popular.
You've got this stylised flower
heads and these
spades from club suits, aren't they?
There are a number of designers that
made these, sort of, things.
There was Voysey and Benson
and there was the
Newlyn school of copper.
Yes, I wondered about that.
Have you seen any markings on it
when you've been cleaning? No.
You'll be more familiar with this than
anybody. No, I've never found a marking.
I think it's going to be
indeterminate as to where it
was made but it's very likely
to have been made
in the Cumbria's metal workshops.
It might be Keswick?
It certainly an Arts and Crafts,
Art Nouveau, 1900 coal bucket.
It cost 10 shillings. Today's value?
One man I talked to thought
it might be 80 to 100.
I think it'd make a bit
over 100, really
but 80 to 100 is about
the right estimate.
How would you feel about that?
Yes, that's all right. Is it?
I've found out something about it
and that's really why I brought it.
Well, that's right and if it makes
a good price, 150, 160...
Even better.
It would, wouldn't it?
I'll buy something I like
that I don't need.
Something you like, that you don't
need. Like a piece of jewellery.
A luxury item? Yes. Very good. Lots
of people are going to like that.
Yeah. Fingers crossed, Damaris.
Thanks for coming. Thank you.
Well, let's hope Damaris can treat
herself to something special.
Now, where is this intriguing
box of Sheila's been hiding?
They've been stuck in a cupboard. Are
they family things? Auntie Bessie's.
Who's Auntie Bessie?
Auntie Bessie died in '97.
She was in her early 90s.
And she used to collect everything,
and when she died the immediate
family got the house but,
because I'd looked after her a lot,
me and another cousin
had the contents.
Oh, that's nice. Tell me about her.
Well, she used to be a photographer,
and during the war,
when the main photographer
had to go away, she took over,
and when they brought the German
generals to windermere, because
there must have been a camp there,
nobody had to take photographs,
so she climbed a tree
and I've got the photographs
of the German generals.
She was a real character.
So is this Auntie Bessie's?
That was Auntie Bessie's. Let's look
and see what we've got. Good idea.
It's going to be a canteen of...
Oh, those are nice, aren't they?
They are beautiful. These are fruit
knives and forks. Yeah.
But it's a set of eight.
You either have six or 12,
you don't have eight.
I don't know that I've ever seen
a set of eight fruit knives
and forks. No, I haven't.
These are mother-of-pearl handles.
Sheffield hallmark for 1930. Right.
And they are hallmarked
by Cooper Brothers.
But the thing I find really
interesting about these
is I wouldn't think these had
ever been used. No.
And now someone will probably buy
them, take them home, think they are
really lovely, put them in a drawer
and they will never get used.
And these will spend their life
never being used.
Yeah, in a drawer. Yeah.
Sad, isn't it? It's very sad, yeah.
They are beautiful.
So what are they going to make,
do you think? I haven't a clue.
Well, because they are not going to
be used, they are almost useless,
I think you should estimate
them at £50-£80
and put a reserve of 40 quid
on them. That's what I think. Yeah.
And it would be nice
if somebody bought Bessie's
fruit knives and forks...
And used them...
and actually got some
use out of them.
That would be lovely, wouldn't it?
We need somebody in a big house.
Absolutely right. A castle.
Keep our fingers crossed.
And talking of big houses,
we couldn't come to lckworth,
now owned by the National Trust,
without taking a closer look
inside the glorious rotunda.
The fourth Earl of Bristol,
who commissioned lckworth,
had two passions,
building and collecting.
The Earl was obsessed with fine art
and antiques, which he
picked up on his travels over the
years on the grand tour of Europe.
And the house was designed to
show off the fruits of his labour.
But sadly, the collection was
destined to remain in Europe.
It was confiscated by
Napoleonic troops in Rome in 1798
and the Earl spent the remaining
years of his life
campaigning for its restitution.
But all was not lost.
Just take a look at this sculpture.
It was commissioned by the Earl when
he met the artist in Rome in 1790.
It depicts the Fury Of Athamas.
According to Greek legend,
in a fit of madness,
Athamas murdered his son.
His wife and their remaining son
then threw themselves into the sea
to escape his fury.
It was confiscated by
the Napoleonic troops
along with the rest
of the collection.
His son, the first Marquis,
was able to buy it back.
It's one of the few works of art
originally picked up by the Earl
that actually made it back here
to lckworth, and I must say it makes
the most marvellous focal point
here in this magnificent rotunda.
I'm sure the Earl would be pleased
to see all the collectables
being brought along
to the west wing today.
Well, Ian, it's always interesting
to see swords coming in
to the programme.
Whenever we have a military
sale at my auction room,
it's amazing how many people have
got swords and guns
and things tucked away that they
feel is a liability
and don't know what to do with.
Can you tell me
where you got them from
and why you decided to bring them
to Flog It?
They were my father-in-law's
and my mother-in-law said
she didn't want them to go to
the youngest grandson because she was
afraid he might cut himself. OK.
So they were given to me and I've had
them for about ten years,
just sat in an umbrella stand.
I'm not a sword man.
I'd rather they went to someone
who would appreciate them. Yeah.
Well, they are the sort of thing
that tends to get hidden
under the bed in a blanket
or on top of the wardrobe or in
an umbrella stand, because people don't
know what to do with them. Exactly.
But there is also a very keen
interest in militaria these days.
And a lot of people
would like to own these,
have them hanging on the wall
or in a cabinet.
People watching are going to say
they are a pair. They are not.
There are slight differences.
There are slight differences,
but they are both light cavalry
swords, 1821 pattern.
This one here is Royal Horse
Artillery and these will be of
the Victorian period, early
Victorian period,
so about 1850, I'd imagine.
Nice to see them in good condition.
The decoration on the blades
is crisp. It's lovely.
Yeah, there's no rusting
and the wire-bound handles,
do you know what that material is?
Shagreen, I think. Very good.
Yeah, sharkskin, shagreen handles.
So quite a luxury item.
These are an officer's sword.
I would think so.
They never saw any actual action,
I would have thought.
They are more a dress officer's
sword. So that's the first one.
And the second one,
very, very similar.
The same pattern and design.
This one's been pulled in
and out of the scabbard a bit more,
had a bit more action.
In fact I can smell the oil on them
still. Still?
Yeah, I just caught
a whiff of it there.
So, like I said, there's a very
ready market for them.
What you think they are worth?
Any ideas?
Well, I honestly thought
they were probably 1930, 1940,
ceremonial dress swords,
brought out for trooping the colour.
And I thought 20 quid? OK.
Well, there's a nice
surprise for you, really.
They are worth about 150 quid each.
What?! Yeah, I think so. Each?
Yes. They are quite a... I like
that reaction! You can come again.
They are nice. There are in good
condition, pretty much.
I suggest put them together and
an estimate combined of £300-£400.
Wow. So... Happy with that?
Very happy.
I think we should put
a reserve on them,
so let's put 300 on them,
shall we? Yeah, no problem.
That gives them every chance...
To go. To go.
Thanks for bringing them
in and fingers crossed,
as the swords are crossed, for a good result.
Good. Thanks very much. Thank you. Cheers.
And that lovely surprise for Ian
rounds up today's items.
Well, there you are, three more
items to take off to auction,
which means it's time to say goodbye
to our magnificent host location,
lckworth House,
and the marvellous architectural
delight of the Rotunda.
We had a brilliant day here,
but let's make our way
over to Diss, to the
auction room for the last time.
And here's what's coming with us.
There's the Arts And Crafts
copper coal bucket,
found in Clitheroe market
for ten shillings.
Will Auntie Bessie's
canteen of fruit knives and forks
find rich pickings
amongst the bidders?
And finally.